<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Failing &amp; perishing of good men a matter of great &amp; sore lamentation : held forth in a sermon preach'd the 26 of June 1662, being the day before the internment of that eminent and faithful gospel-preacher, Mr. John Sympson.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F93A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40573</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19368255</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19368255</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1669:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Failing &amp; perishing of good men a matter of great &amp; sore lamentation : held forth in a sermon preach'd the 26 of June 1662, being the day before the internment of that eminent and faithful gospel-preacher, Mr. John Sympson.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 40.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Simpson, John, d. 1662 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108795:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Failing &amp; Perishing OF GOOD MEN A Matter of Great &amp; ſore Lamentation.</p>
            <p>Held forth in A SERMON Preach'd the 26 of <hi>June</hi> 1662. Being the day before the INTERMENT OF THAT Eminent and Faithful GOSPEL PREACHER, Mr. John Sympſon.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 10.7.</hi>
                  </bibl> The memory of the juſt is bleſſed; but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 116.15.</hi>
                  </bibl> Precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of his Saints.</p>
            </q>
            <q>Accuſator qui confortem defert, ſeſe iutueatur.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:108795:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108795:2"/>
            <head>To the Church of Chriſt, and every member thereof, over which Mr. <hi>Iohn Sympſon</hi> was made (by the Holy-ſpirit) over-ſeer.</head>
            <head type="sub">Grace and Peace be multiplied unto you, thorow the knowledge of God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in the Lord!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF I ſhould ſpend much time in making an Apologie for my ſelf in reference to the Dedication of this following Diſcourſe to you of the Congregation, I might well be judged to complement. It's yours by right: If it come into other hands (through God's bleſſing) it may do good, but as in the preaching of it I had, ſo now in the Printing of it I have a ſpecial reſpect for you, and to you of the Church it was firſt preach'd, and now printed for your ſakes.</p>
            <p>However I think meet in this place, to give ſome brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the reaſon both of its Publication and Dedication. Firſt, for its Publication, the reaſon is manifold: <hi>1.</hi> For that I did judge the ſubject in it ſelf to be ſuitable to the preſent ſtate of the people of God, and might be of uſe to the ſtirring them up to humiliation and reformation. <hi>2.</hi> That I might manifeſt that dear reſpect I had for, and that affection I did
<pb facs="tcp:108795:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>bear unto that choice ſervant of Chriſt deceaſed, under whoſe Miniſtry I have been ſo often refreſhed and raiſed in my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe I was deſired by ſeveral of the friends of Mr. <hi>Iohn Sympſon,</hi> either to print my diſcourſe, or give them copies of it; wherefore I choſe to do the former, becauſe I did judge it might give the greater ſatiſfaction. 4thly, That I might do ſomething towards the vindication of the name of that glorified ſaint, both from former, and later re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and ſlanders. Thoſe that have a good conſcience, have not always a good name. The people of God in this life are called the troublers of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> they are ſeditious, rebellious, what not? Christ himſelf was accounted a deceiver, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſter; and <hi>Paul</hi> was ſaid to be aſeditious perſon, and ſuffered (in the opin on of ſome) as an evill doer, <hi>2 Tim. 2.9.</hi> Wherein I ſuffer trouble as an evil doer, even unto bonds. <hi>Job</hi> was repreſented unto the world as an hypocrite, and that by his friends; which went very near him. The miniſters of the Goſpell must expect above any other to meet with reproaches <hi>(2 Cor. 6, 8.)</hi> the Devill hates them most, becauſe they most oppoſe his Kingdom, and interest; and therefore if he can't debauch their conſciences, hee'l ſpit his venom at them through the mouths of wicked and ungodly men. But let wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men know, that the time is haſtening on apace, wherein as God will make inquiſition for blood, ſo for names; as the death, ſo the name of a ſaint is pretious in Gods accompt: God will roul away the reproach of his people; *
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.6.</note> hee'l cauſe their innocency and righteouſneſs to break forth as the ſun at noon, * and their names ſhall be had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. I had thought ſomething might have been done this way by a better pen before this time, but it being ſeverall months ſince the death of Mr. <hi>Sympſon,</hi> and nothing done, I was willing to make publique what I had preacht; &amp; I hope it is not out of the pride and haughtineſs my heart, (though a proud, and wicked heart I have, and bleſſed be free grace that in any meaſure I know it ſo to be, but to do Chriſt and his people ſervice. The ſoul of our dear brother
<pb facs="tcp:108795:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>is in glory, above any Encomiuas or Eulogie that can be made of him: What therefore is ſpoken in the following diſcourſe, extends not to him, but unto the living; it's not to advantage him, but to prevent others from diſadvantaging themſelves by thinking or ſpeaking evilly of him. Laſtly, That I might preſent the virtues of Mr. <hi>Sympſon</hi> to you for your imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Undoubtedly it's your duty to follow him ſo far as he followed Chriſt. Now there were very many choice things in that faithful man, worthy of emulation and imitation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you will do well to walk, as you had him for an example. Thus m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch for its publication.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons why I did dedicate it to you of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are, Firſt, Becauſe I did judge the Diſpenſation of God to which the following Diſcourſe refers, did more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern you, than any other: it's true, there are many not of the Congregation, that did undoubtedly receive good by Mr. <hi>Sympſons</hi> Miniſtry, and will have cauſe to bleſs God for it unto all Eternity; and theſe are much concerned in his death: But however, conſidering his relation unto you, how he was under Chriſt your Biſhop, Faſtor, Feeder, Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how faithful, conſtant and laborious he was in the diſcharge of his truſt committed to him, it muſt needs be granted, that that Providence of God did moſt nearly concern you, and conſequently this following Diſcourſe. <hi>2.</hi> Its to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my thank, fulneſs to God and you, for all thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sious dayes and hours which I have enjoyed in your Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. To my beſt remembrance I never ſaw nor enjoyed more of the preſence and glory of God in any Aſſembly (ſetting the Min-ſtry of Mr. <hi>Bridge</hi> of <hi>Yarmouth</hi> aſide) than I have done in your Aſſemblies. The conſideration of which, as it doth in the firſt place oblige me to bleſs the Lord (in whom all my Well-ſprings are, and who is the Fountain of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his people) ſo in the next place it doth engage me to ſerve you his people (with, and among whom I have enjoyed ſuch great mercies) to the utmoſt of my abilities. By this
<pb facs="tcp:108795:4"/>Dedication I do not profeſs to have paid my Engagements un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I do onely take an occaſion hereby to acknowledge my ſelf your Debtor. Pay my Engagements I cannot bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then by praying for you. My hearty deſire therefore to God for you is, That you all may know, love and enjoy Chriſt in truth, that every member of your viſible Body may (by the Spirit) be baptized into that one Myſtical Body, over which Chriſt is the Head, that Hell may be never the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler for any of you, but that you may all live graciouſly, which is the way to dye bleſſedly. And further, that God would keep you together, and hide you in the ſecret of his preſence, cauſe his glory to reſt upon you, and cauſe a defence to be upon that his glory, that he would give you Paſtors af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own heart, and annoint them with a double meaſure of his Spirit, a ſpirit fit both to rule and teach; to rule I ſay (not as Lords over your conſciences, but) according to the bleſſed direction of Scripture-Canons; that ſo you may be able to bleſs God in the words of <hi>Ezra,</hi> (cap. <hi>9.8.</hi>) And now for a little ſpace grace hath been ſhewed from the Lord our God, to leave us a Remnant to eſcape, and to give us a Nail in his holy Place, that our God may lighten our eyes, and give us a little reviving in our bondage,</p>
            <p>All I deſire (which <hi>I</hi> am ſure <hi>I</hi> ſhal have) is your acceptance of this my love in the Lord. <hi>I</hi> can't ſay that <hi>I</hi> do here preſent unto you the ſame Sermon (verbatim) that you heard preacht; For, beſides thoſe neceſſary diſtinctions that muſt be put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Tongue and the Pen, <hi>I</hi> hàve ſuperadded ſome things for the perfecting this Diſcourſe, which <hi>I</hi> think you will not judge uſeleſs or needleſs when you ſhall have read it.</p>
            <p>When ought of Truth is preſented unto you, take heed of looking too much upon the hand that brings it, or upon the dreſs in which it comes; not upon the hand, becauſe then if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument that preſents it, be accounted unworthy, Truth will be deſpiſed: He that preſents you with this following diſcourſe, is a very unworthy inſtrument, as unworthy as you can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb facs="tcp:108795:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>him to be; though bleſſed be God, how vile ſoever he be in other mens eyes, he deſires to be more vile in his own: But yet <hi>I</hi> hope you have learnt with the holy Prophet, to be content to be fed, though it be by a Raven; it's no matter who brings truth, ſo God ſends it; though withall <hi>I</hi> would here give you this caution, Take heed of going out of Gods way for feeding. <hi>I</hi> conclude that that man that reſolves to go to <hi>Rome</hi> to learn the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, hath met with ſome bad counſel. Keep in thy way, and have thy Touchſtone alwayes ready, and then (with the Goldſmith) when ought is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto thee, firſt try it, and if it prove right and ſound, take it, and bleſs God for it, and mind not the perſon that brings it; but take heed of going out of thy ſhop, for it may be whilſt thou art trading in other mens ſhops, thine own may be robbed.</p>
            <p>Again, Mind not the dreſs in which Truth comes. Many have ſuch critical ſtomachs, that plain wholeſome fare will not down with them, notwithſtanding times are hard, and bread dear, yet they muſt have food in ſuch a dreſs, or elſe they are not pleaſed; they'le be ready to ſlight ſuch food as the Countrey people would be glad of with all their heart: <hi>I</hi> dare not invite one ſuch perſon to my little Feaſt, and that becauſe <hi>I</hi> fear there's not one bit will pleaſe him. I am plain, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe: <hi>I</hi> dare ſay the following diſcourſe is whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; if therefore wholeſom food will pleaſe thee, eat, and much good may do thee. As to this particular <hi>I</hi> would only beg you, To look back and conſider thoſe many exhortations you had from that bleſſed man Mr. <hi>Cradock,</hi> to keep cloſe to the plainneſs and ſimplicity of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>To cloſe: My dearly beloved, you are a people greatly bleſt of God, with reſpect to the means of Grace; your conſtant helps (for above theſe twenty years) have been glorious helps; your Auxiliary helps (which you have had in abundance) have been glorious helps. Conſidering one thing with another, <hi>I</hi> think <hi>I</hi> may ſay and not ſin, you have enjoyed the Cream of the world: Surely Friends, God expects great things from you, expects you ſhould be eminent Chriſtians; Eminent, <hi>1.</hi> In thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb facs="tcp:108795:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>the high praiſes of God ſhould be in your mouths, for that he hath dealt ſo bountifully with you. <hi>2.</hi> Eminent in fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; Unfruitſulneſs under ſuch means, ſoon fits the ſoul for curſing and burning; <hi>Iſa. 5. Mat. 3.10. Heb. 6, 7, 8. 3.</hi> Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in faithfulneſs; and that, <hi>1.</hi> in reſpect to ſincerity, <hi>Phil. 1.10.</hi> You ſhould not do things to be ſeen of men, but as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes under Gods eye. <hi>2.</hi> In reſpact of conſtancy, Rev. <hi>2.10.</hi> Be <hi>faithful unto the death, and I will give thee a Crown of Life.</hi> The Sermons thou haſt heard, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt that have preacht unto thee, will all witneſs againſt thee, if thou ſhalt turn Apost ate, Conſider theſe things and do accordingly, and it will be well with you now, better anon, and best of all at last. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108795:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The periſhing and failing of good men, a matter of great and ſore lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joh. 11.35.</hi>
                  </bibl> Jeſus wept.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS every thing is beautiful in its ſeaſon, ſo words when ſpoken in due ſeaſon, are <hi>like apples of gold in pictures of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> And therefore it is the great work of a Preacher to conſider the ſtate of the people to whom he preaches, ſo to prepare his work before hand, as that he may hit the mark, knock the nail on the head: The Preacher ſought out acceptable words; now generally thoſe words are moſt acceptable to, and beſt received by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers (eſpecially intelligent hearers) that are ſuited to their preſent condition. Good words may be vain words in a preachers mouth, and they are ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſo, when they are either inconſiſtant to the argument in hand, or elſe altogether unſuitable to the capacity and ſtate of the hearers. I conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore the ſecret hand of God upon this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108795:6"/>in taking away that eminent Servant of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>John Sympſon,</hi> thought it incumbent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to ſpeak ſomething at this time that might be ſuitable to the preſent diſpenſation of God towards you, and in my meditations this Scripture was caſt in, <hi>Jeſus wept.</hi> The occaſion of this text is known unto you; in the begining of this Chapter you read that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was ſick, and the news thereof imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly ſent to <hi>Jeſus;</hi> who notwithſtanding he dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loved him, yet (as the ſequel of the ſtory acquaints you) he doth not preſently go up to <hi>Bethany</hi> to viſit ſick <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but maketh a ſtay for ſeveral days; the reaſon whereof is at hand, <hi>viz.</hi> That a ſentence of death might paſs upon beloved <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and he be laid in the grave, and a ſtone rouled upon him; and all this in order to the manifeſtation of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and power of Chriſt in his reſurrection. It is good here to note, that as Chriſt here dealt with <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ſo he doth often deal with his beloved Spouſe, his Church on earth: the Church ſhe is ſick, lieth lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, and nigh to death; report hereof is made to Chriſt in heaven, and he is deſired to come and viſit his ſick Spouſe; Chriſt, though he loves his Spouſe with a dear immutable love, yet he ſeemeth to turn a deaf ear upon this requeſt, and carrieth it as if he did not mind <hi>Zions</hi> concernments, as if he cared not how ſhe was abuſed and trampled on by this wicked perſecuting world; but the reaſon (as above) lieth here, that ſo a ſentence of death might paſs upon the Church, and upon all her concerns and glory; and all this in order to the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts glorious power in her reſurrection,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108795:6"/>that he may appear to be the great God, that can raiſe deliverance out of the duſt, appear for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple when there is none ſhut up or left.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Lazarus</hi> had been in the grave four days, Chriſt he comes up to <hi>Bethany,</hi> and the ſiſters of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> viz. <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> they come out to meet <hi>Jeſus;</hi> firſt <hi>Martha</hi> ſhe cometh, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. and ſhe ſaith, <hi>Lord, if thou hadſt been here, my brother had not died,</hi> ver. 21. After this comes <hi>Mary,</hi> verſ. 32. and ſhe falls down at Chriſts feet, ſaying, <hi>Lord, if thou hadſt been here, my brother, had not died. When Jeſus therefore ſaw her weeping, and the Jews alſo weeping which came with her, he groaned in the Spirit, and was troubled, and ſaid, Where have ye laid him? They ſay unto him, Lord, come and ſee. Jeſus wept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is very much wrapt up in the bowels of this little Text:
<note place="margin">The text opened.</note> Here we may take notice of the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chriſt; it appears by Chriſts weeping that he is perfect man, as well as perfect God. That Chriſt wept, is to be referred, not to his Divinity, but to his Humanity; and ſo we ſhall find that Chriſt was ſubject as to this, ſo to all natural infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; as hunger, thirſt, wearineſs, &amp;c. which may comfort the Saints that groan under natural, as well as ſinful infirmities; and that from the reaſon why Chriſt was made in all things like unto his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; namely, <hi>That he might be a merciful High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt, Hebr.</hi> 2.17, 18. And though Chriſt be now in glory, yet he is touched with the feeling of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of his people here on earth, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.15. ſo touched, as that he cannot but have compaſſion on them under all their preſſures and grievances whatſoever.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:108795:7"/>
            <p>Do'ſt thou then groan under natural weakneſſes and infirmities? Go boldly to the throne of grace, (which is the uſe the Apoſtle makes of this doctrin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16.) and ſpread thy weakneſſes and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities before the Lord, and thou maieſt in faith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect grace to help in this need, that Chriſt ſhould enable thee to bear up under theſe weakneſſes, until mortality ſhall have put on immortality.</p>
            <p>But to come to the thing I intend, and that is the occaſion of Chriſts weeping, which was the death of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> a good man: whence I ſhal obſerve and proſecute this Doctrine;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That it is a Chriſt like frame of ſpirit, to be deeply af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with, and to mourn over the death of ſuch as are truly gracious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's <hi>Lazarus</hi> a good man in his grave, and Chriſt he weeps over him: you have a weeping Chriſt over a dead <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When old <hi>Jacob</hi> an eminent perſon was buryed; it's ſaid <hi>Gen.</hi> 50:10: (<hi>That they mourned with a great and ſore lamentation,</hi> and that for 7 dayes together. And ſo when <hi>Moſes</hi> (that eminent ſervant of the Lord, that brought the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> very neer to the good Land) died, and was buried by a ſecret hand, it's ſaid, <hi>the children of Iſrael mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for him</hi> 30 <hi>days,</hi> Deut. 34.8.</p>
            <p>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eerly beloved, you have loſt a <hi>Moſes,</hi> one that was valiant for God in former times, when the people of God in <hi>England</hi> were coming out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> &amp; he hath been an eminent leader to the ſaints in their wilderneſs ſtate, and God did often take him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108795:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to the top of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> and gave him their glorious viſions, and that not onely of heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> but alſo of that glorious land of reſt and righteouſneſs that the Saints ſhall injoy in this world, when the mountain of the houſe of the Lord ſhall be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upon the top of all mountains, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world become the Kingdomes of the Lord, and of his Chriſt; of which things he hath often ſpoke unto you in much life and power. Now that ſuch a <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould be taken off in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, while the people of God are yet ſhort of this good Land, is matter of great humiliation.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe you find the ſame ſpirit in thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. that <hi>Paul</hi> (the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles) did there take his farewel of, ſaying, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>And now behold, I know that ye all, among whom I have gone preaching the Kingdom of God, ſhall ſee my face no more.</hi> It's ſaid, 37, 38 verſes, <hi>And they all wept ſore, and fell on Pauls neck, and kiſſed him: Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing moſt of all for the words which he ſpake [that they ſhould ſee his face no more]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> alſo is exceedingly affected in this kind, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Help Lord, for the godly man ceaſeth, for the faithful fail from among the children of men.</hi> And ſo the Church, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. <hi>Wo is me, for I am as when they have gathered the ſummer-fruits, as the grape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleanings of the Vintage; there is no cluſter in me— The good man is periſhed out of the earth: and there is none upright, among men, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 57. verſ. 1. laments and bemoans the ſpiritual ſecurity of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> expreſt by this, That they did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108795:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; take notice, neither were they affected with the periſhing &amp; taking away of the righteous, and the merciful man, and chargeth upon them this ſenceleſs and ſtupid frame of heart, as their great and common ſin.</p>
            <p>Now by all this it appears, that it is both the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and property of a Chriſtian (ſuch an one as hath been baptized into the ſpirit of Jeſus) to be deeply affected with the death of ſuch as are truly gratious, eſpecially when they are eminent for uſe and ſervice to Chriſt, and his people.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> We ſhall now give you the reaſons why it is ſo, and cannot be otherwiſe, but that gracious perſons muſt needs be affected with, and mourn over the death of good men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Becauſe every ſtroke in this kind, puts a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious heart in mind of its mortality, tells us that we are dying mortall creatures, and that's a very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration to every awakened ſoul. <hi>The li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, the living will lay it to heart,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccle. 7.2. The ſtroke of death upon others, tells us that dye we muſt, and how ſoon the Lord knows; and O happy! thrice happy is that perſon that can dye wel: We are ready to ſay, bleſſed is the rich man, and the honourable man, and the profeſſing man; the man that can ſpeak wel, and pray well, and live well; but above all (ſay I) bleſſed is the perſon that dyes well. Now ſuch ſtrokes as theſe puts a ſerious ſoul in mind of dying. Ther's none preſent knows who may dye next, may go to the grave next. That's the Firſt; but then,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 It ſprings from that Simpathy that is both in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108795:8"/>nature, and in grace: firſt in nature, when God takes away a husband, a father, a child, &amp;c. this cuts deep, and affects much. <hi>Abraham</hi> he mourns over beloved <hi>Sarah. David</hi> over <hi>Abſolon,</hi> though a rebellious ſon. To be ſtupid, and not to mind the hand of God when he ſmites our near and dear relations, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that we do not onely want grace, but natural affection; and to be without natural affection, is a very black character, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p>And then in Grace there is alſo a great ſympathy: If God ſmites one member of the Church, the reſt are affected with it: If a <hi>Paul,</hi> a Miniſter of Chriſt, a Paſtor, a ſpiritual Father, comes to take his fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of his people, and tell them that they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee his face more; oh what weeping, and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and lamenting is there at his departure!</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3dly, Another reaſon is, Becauſe there is much of God's anger oft times to be ſeen in ſuch ſtrokes of God's anger; I ſay, not againſt the perſons taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but againſt thoſe that remain; As when God taketh away a Father, a Husband, a Wife, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the ſoul of that Relation may be carryed to Heaven, and there poſſeſſed of glory, and yet nevertheleſs the death of that Relation may be in judgement to the Family. And ſo in a ſpiritual Relation, God may take away a holy Miniſter, a faithful Paſtor, and this in judgement to the Flock, to thoſe that ſate under his Miniſtry: And ſurely it is the great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of you of this Congregation to hear the voice of this Rod, and of him that hath appointed it, and to endeavour to know the mind of God in this great ſtroke.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:108795:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="4">4thly, The periſhing of good men is a matter of great humiliation, and that becauſe they are a great bleſſing to the nations, cities, families, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where they are caſt. It fares either the better, or the worſe with ſuch places for their ſake. When God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the old world, the family of <hi>Neah</hi> was ſaved for <hi>Noahs</hi> ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. And God hath promiſed to bleſs them that bleſs his people, and curſe them that curſe his people. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12:3: &amp; 27:29 <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.9. Wo then to the ranting damning crew of this generation; who make it a matter of ſport to curſe the ſaints of the moſt high; for as ſure as God is in heaven (without true repentance) thoſe curſes will return upon there one heads,</p>
            <p>The ſtory likewiſe of <hi>Abimelech</hi> is remarkable, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. it's ſaid, <hi>God faſt cloſed up all the wombs of the houſe of Abimelech, becauſe of Sarah Abrahams wife,</hi> ver. 18th. and ver. 7, <hi>God himſelf ſaith to Abimelech, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the man (meaning Abraham) his wife, for he is a prophet, and he ſhall pray for thee; and thou ſhalt live: and if thou reſtore her not, know you, that thou ſhalt ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dye, thou, and all that are thine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover you read that God bleſſed the houſe of <hi>Potipher,</hi> and all that he had for <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5 <hi>verſes.</hi> And the houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> was bleſt for the ark ſake, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 6.10, 11. And the Citie of <hi>Zoar</hi> was ſaved for <hi>Lets</hi> ſake, that he might have a refuge to flie unto, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 19. and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> 11.10.11. ſaith thus, When it goeth well with the righteous, the city rejoyces: and when the wicked periſh, there is ſhouting. By the bleſſing of the upright the city is exalted: but it is overthrown by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108795:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the mouth of the wicked. Surely then, if the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty rejoyceth, and is exalted by the bleſſing, and proſperity of the righteous, thoſe rulers and great men of the earth, that have endeavored, or ſhall endeavour to eſtabliſh themſelves in their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, power, and glory, by the impriſoning, &amp; ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, of the ſaints, are exceedingly blinded, and infatuated; for by this they diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be of the ſpirit of <hi>Haman;</hi> who could not be contented with his name, and honour, ſo long as <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſate at the Kings gate: ſo they, they have not been content with their greatneſs, ſo long as the people of God have had any breathing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, but ſtill have deſigned the building of themſelves, and their kingdomes, upon the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of ſuch, of whom this world is not worthy: It had been well for ſuch, if they had ſeriouſly conſidered the juſt judgement of God, upon this proud <hi>Haman,</hi> he ſought his own advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deſigned that, and he was advanced, with a witneſs; for he was hanged upon a Gallows fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cubits high.</p>
            <p>Mind alſo theſe Scriptures, wherein this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular is further proved, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.24 <hi>In that day ſhall Iſrael be the third with Egypt and with Aſſyria, even a bleſſing in the midſt of the land.</hi> Ezek. 34.25.26. <hi>And</hi> I <hi>will make with them a covenant of peace, and will cauſe the evill beaſts to ceaſe out of the land: and they ſhall dwell ſafely in the wilderneſs, and ſleep in the woods. And</hi> I <hi>will make them, and the places round about my hill, a bleſſing; and I will cauſe the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108795:10"/>ſhower to come down in his ſeaſon: there ſhall be ſhowers of bleſsing.</hi> Micah 5.7. <hi>And the remnant of Jacob ſhall be in the midſt of many people, as a dew from the Lord, as the ſhowers upon the graſſe, that tarrieth not for man, nor waiteth for the ſons of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which ſcripture the great encreaſe the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall have in, and the great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſhall be unto the nations of the world, is prophecied of.</p>
            <p>The people of God muſt needs be a bleſſing to the places where they dwell; for.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, There is God eſpecially preſent: that land that is planted with righteous people, may be rightly called <hi>Jehovah Shammah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48. <hi>ult. Pſal.</hi> 46.5.</note> for the Lord is there. God is in the midſt of her, &amp;c. But.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 Righteous ones are the ſtrength and ſafety of the nations where they are, the pillars indeed upon which the world ſtand: and to ſpeak the truth, the world is ſaved for their ſakes. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>God there ſaith, <hi>That if one man could be found in Jeruſalem that did execute judgment, and ſought the truth, he would pardon it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words two things are to be noted: Firſt, that the people of God were at this time reduced to a very ſmall number, and thoſe that were,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.25. <hi>to the end.</hi>
               </note> were hid, could not be ſeen; for <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.12—<hi>but when the wicked riſe, a man is hidden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rulers and magiſtrates at this time were as bad as hell, Divels incarnate; and when there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108795:10"/>are ſuch magiſtrates, then righteous perſons muſt lye hid, there is no appearing for them at ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proverbs</hi> 28. ult. <hi>when the wicked riſe, men (that is good men) hid themſelves: but when they periſh, the righteous increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But. 2, and to the purpoſe, by (a man) in this text, we are to underſtand, that a very few, a ſmall number of righteous ones ſhould ſerve to ſave the city.</p>
            <p>And anſwerable to this,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.</note> you have God conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to the prayer of <hi>Abraham</hi> concerning <hi>Sodom</hi> ſo low, that if there were but 10 right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous perſons to be found in it, yet he would ſave the city for the ſake of thoſe ten righteous. And although there was but one righteous perſon to be found in <hi>Sodom,</hi> namely <hi>Lot,</hi> (and therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> This one fellow, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.9:) yet Gods hands were ſo tyed, and bound up by this one righteous man, that he could not deſtroy <hi>Sodom,</hi> untill <hi>Lot</hi> was got ſafe to <hi>Zoar;</hi> for, ſaith the Angel to <hi>Lot,</hi> verſe 22. Haſt thee, eſcape thither; (for I cannot do any thing) till thou be come thither, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The people of God by their prayers &amp; tears preſerve the places wherein they live from wrath and judgement, as appears by theſe ſcriptures, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Exo.</hi> 32.11.12.13.14, 31.32. &amp; 33.12.13. &amp; 34:8:9: <hi>Deut.</hi> 9:18. to the end <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 7:7:8:9:1: <hi>Sam.</hi> 23: <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.17. &amp; 14:7:8, 9, 19: to the end; <hi>Lamen:</hi> 1.16. And although
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108795:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>it's poſſible the ſin of a nation, or people may be ſo very great,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chion.</hi> 36.16.</note> of ſuch a Scarlet die, and cloathed with ſuch circumſtances, as that God may not hear the prayers of his righteous ones for that nation or people, (<hi>as Jer.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14.) but pour out his wrath upon them without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie; * yet nevertheleſs ſuch is the prevalency of the ſaints with God in prayer, as that we find, when deſtruction and ruine hath been threatned, and hath ſeemed to be entring in at the windows, and at the door, the prayers and interceſſions of righteous ones (they ſlinging themſelves in the gap, and pleading with God upon the account of his name, honour and mercy) hath diverted judgement, and procured national mercy and pardon many a time: And again, ſuch is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of ſaints in prayer, as that if God be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to deſtroy a nation, he firſt reſtrains the ſpirit of prayer; he ſaith to his holy ones, <hi>pray not for this people for their good, (Jer. chap.</hi> 7.16. &amp; 11.14. &amp; 14.11.) <hi>and let me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that my wrath may wax hot againſt them, and that</hi> I <hi>may conſume them,</hi> (Exod. 32.10.) as much as to ſay, Give me my hands at liberty, and do not tye me up from deſtroying this people. I can't deſtroy while <hi>Moſes</hi> doth thus pray, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Moſes</hi> hold thy peace; ceaſe praying, that I may devour, and deſtroy.</p>
            <p>Yet once more, ſuch is the prevalency of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that if there be a ſpirit of Faith and Prayer in the Saints on the behalf of a Nation, or people, it's almoſt an infallible ſign that God will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108795:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>but have mercy upon that people. The prayers of the Saints (with holy reverence be it ſpoken) do overcome the Almighty; ſo that God cannot withſtand the faith and prayer of his people, and the reaſon lieth here; Becauſe they wreſtle with God in his own ſtrength, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the Almighty in almighty ſtrength, and ſo muſt needs be prevailers.</p>
            <p>Well then might <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſay of <hi>Elijah</hi> (that mighty man of prayer) when he was taken up to heaven, <hi>[the chariot of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof]</hi> and alſo King <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſay the ſame of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha,</hi> when he lay ſick of his deadly ſickneſs; For that indeed the ſtrength of a Nation lyeth not in chariots and horſemen, in towers and caſtles, &amp;c. but in the prayers of the [Faithful] of the land. It's not the Common-prayers of the common ſwearers and drunkards that will ſecure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe a people, but the fervent prayers of righteous ones. Wicked ſwearers, Drunkards, Adulterers, Idolaters and truce-breakers are the plague and curſe of a Nation; but holy, believing and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ones, they are the bleſſing of a Nation. A Nation is more beholding to the meaneſt Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin-maid in it, that hath in her a ſpirit of prayer, then to a thouſand of her profane ſwaggering Gentry; ſuch Gentry that are better at whoring, ſwearing and drinking, then they are at praying. When they are drunk they'l curſe and ban the people of God to the pit of hell; but alas, the people of God (in a holy ſenſe) doth laugh them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108795:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſcorn: they'l put the prayers, and tears, and ſighs of one righteous perſon, againſt ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of theſe poor ſelf-deſtroyers; and will be confident that the prayers and tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of that one perſon (be he a Cobler, or a Tinker, or be ſhe a Kitchin maid, as aboveſaid) ſhal do them more good, then ten thouſand of them ſhall do hurt by all their oaths and curſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe profane wretches, are ready to wiſh the people of God all out of the world, but alas! what would then theſe wretches do? they are beholding to the ſaints for their very beings, and for the continuance of all their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>When God hath but once gathered in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and done his work in <hi>Zion,</hi> he will ſoon pull the world about theſe mens ears: If the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous be taken away, <hi>he is taken away from the evill to come, (Iſa</hi> 57:1:) Wo to <hi>Sodom,</hi> if <hi>Lot</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; and ſo I may ſay, Wo to <hi>England,</hi> if the righteous ſhould be taken away; Wo to <hi>London,</hi> whenever thou ceaſeſt to be a refuge to the ſaints, whenever thy gates ſhall be ſhut againſt the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and people of the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ten thouſand woes to that man, family, citie, or nation, that engageth againſt the prayers of the Saints; that ſeeks to defend and maintain that intereſt which the Saints do (by Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule) pray againſt, and believe muſt go down. If I know my heart, I would not be in the condition
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108795:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of ſuch for the whole world. Blind fools! do they think to ſtand againſt the faith and praiers of the Saints, which (in a holy ſenſe) overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God himſelf? If they do, they may find themſelvs miſtaken when it is too late.</p>
            <p>The children of Iſrael, though they ſlighted and deſpiſed the Prophets, would in time of deſtreſs come to them for prayer, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.8.9. &amp; 12.19. Yea <hi>Pharoah,</hi> as proud, and as high as he was, yet when the plague was upon him, <hi>Moſes</hi> he muſt be ſent for, and be entreated to pray for him, and his people.</p>
            <p>The time may come, when the proudeſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor on earth, may ſee cauſe to beg the prayers of ſuch whom he now perſecutes.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the reaſons of the doctrine, ſhewing why the people of God muſt needs be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with, and mourn over the death of praying and believing ones.</p>
            <p>Wee ſhall now proceed to application.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> And firſt it affords matter of information; as Firſt, if it be a Chriſt like frame to mourn over the death of ſuch as are truly gracious, it informs us, how unlike to Chriſt ſuch are; who though they plead for Chriſtian buriall, yet do attend fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſolemnities with a vain, wicked, ungodly ſpirit, and carriage, making the houſe of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a houſe of laughter, and filling themſelves with wine (wherein is exceſs) until they become more like beaſts then men, which is a practice that may be found, not onely among the poor
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108795:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ignorant country people, but too often in this great city.</p>
            <p>You may ſoon judge how fit ſuch perſons are to attend upon a funerall Sermon; but indeed I am apt to think, funerall Sermons have generally been rather for oſtentation, and vain glory, then for profit.</p>
            <p>Hereby is likewiſe condemned that heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh practice of ringing of bells ſo ſoon as ever funeral ſolemnites are performed:</p>
            <p>How unſuitable is it, that ſo ſoon as ever the husband, or wife, or a godly friend is laid in the earth, to ſet the bells a ringing, which imports matter of joy rather then of ſorrow?</p>
            <p>I am preaching now to a people, who have by a profeſſion ſeparated themſelves from the world, and the traditions thereof; you'l do well to keep your ground in theſe evil dayes, and ſo to educate and bring up your children as that they alſo may be delivered from theſe ſnares, But</p>
            <p n="2">2 If it be a Chriſt like frame of ſpirit to bewail the periſhing of good men, it informs us how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to Chriſt that ſpirit is, whereby men do cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and reproach good men when taken away by death.</p>
            <p>And I do the rather mention this, becauſe ſome have taken the boldneſs to judge and cenſure this pretious ſervant of Chriſt now in glory, and to ſpeak very unworthily concerning him, ſince his death:</p>
            <p>Oh dreadfull how unlike to Chriſt is this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108795:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>thou that ſhouldſt be judging &amp; condemning thy ſelf for non improvement of ſo great a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, artjudging this eminent ſervant of Chriſt now dead. The Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> wil teach theebetter; for let perſonsbe never ſo vile in their lives, yet when they come to be laid in the grave, then they are dear brethren &amp; ſiſters. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider you that are of this ſpirit, how ſad it will be if this ſervant of Chriſt ſhall appear as a witneſs againſt you at the great day of account, if the ſermons that he preach'd, &amp; the profers of grace that God made by him, ſhal witneſs againſt thee, and thou then be judged, condemned, and ſent to hell for not receiving, entertaining, and improving the precious ſermons of this glorified ſaint. It's poſſible now you that judge and condemn him, and ſpeak more then you know, or more then is truth of him, and that poſſibly to carnall and wicked perſons, you may have your tale heard, &amp; it may be pleaſing to wicked prophane people, that he ſhould be ſo judged by his own followers, but at the great day of Chriſt there wil be none to hear a tale againſt him: at that day, God will clear his innocency before men and Angels, and it ſhall appear to all the world, that he was a true and a faithful ſervant of Chriſt, when it may be ſome of thoſe that do now judge him, ſhall then be condemned for notorious hypocrits, and it ſhall appear, that (notwithſtanding all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and pretended Zeal for the name, and glory of God,) they were workers of iniquity,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108795:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſuch who did live in the love of ſome accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſin or other.</p>
            <p>O therefore away with this ſpirit, to hell with it, for from thence it came. Let it ſuffice that this glorified ſaint ſuffered much in this kind while he was living: I am apt to think the heats, and paſſions, and raſh cenſures of profeſſors, hath made him oft go home with a ſad heart, and coſt him many a tear in private: let this his ſuffering ſuffice, let not his name ſuffer now he is dead: ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to be quiet in his grave: Leave his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Lord, and let it be your work to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe many pretious ſermons that he hath in the fear of his God preach'd unto you.</p>
            <p>As to the matter of his taking the Oaths of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and Supremacy upon his releaſment out of Priſon,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>About</hi> Mr. Sympſon's <hi>taking the Oaths.</hi>
               </note> which hath occaſioned ſo much talk, I ſhall onely ſay theſe two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that in Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> time, theſe Oaths were taken and plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for; and that not onely by the faith and troth Chriſtians, but even by the Non-conformiſts of thoſe times, who were eminent for God in their day, and whoſe names are yet pretious among the Lords people, &amp; who are known (by their works) to be men greatly inlightned in the myſteries of the Goſpel. Now although I do not look upon their example to be binding to the ſaints in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, or a ſufficient rule for our practice, yet I judge the conſideration not onely of the great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, but alſo of the clear light that many of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108795:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe (who did them take the Oaths with great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ faction) had in the word of God, may a little take off the edge of that bitter ſpirit that is in many profeſſors againſt their brethren for theſe things; for that it cannot be judged otherwiſe, but that many who did take theſe Oaths with great ſatiſfaction, are now in glory: But</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Who made thee Lord over thy Brother's Conſcience? Muſt all profeſſors be condemned by thee, becauſe they cannot ſee with thy eyes, and tread in thy ſteps? By what authority doeſt thou impoſe thy particular light and perſwaſion upon thy brother; &amp; that ſo, as almoſt to un-ſaint him without conformity? This impoſing ſpirit is an Antichriſtian ſpirit evermore. How unlike thy ſelf doſt thou act, when notwithſtanding thou pleadeſt for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, yet thou ſhalt impoſe thine own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions upon thy brother after this rare: Such impoſing ſpirits (let their proteſſions be what they will) are not to be confided in; for it may well be feared, that thoſe that can ſo readily take away the good name of a godly man, becauſe he cannot conform to their Light, would take away his eſtate and liberty alſo upon the very ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, were it in their power.
<note place="margin">Note.</note> Indeed thoſe men are greatly to be lamented that ſhall ſin againſt Light, againſt avowed principles, againſt ſolemn covenants and engagements, ſhall do that which is clean contrary to their own doctrines and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions; I mean, when thoſe avowed principles,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108795:15"/>folemn covenants, doctrines and aſſertions have been according to the Word of God. But thus did not this faithful man, he did nothing in this matter but what was according to his Light; and that is evident, for that ſeveral months before his impriſonment he did publickly declare his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be for, and not againſt the taking of theſe Oaths, and did plead it while in priſon with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral friends; and when he came before the Court, the matter lying ſo, that either he muſt take the Oaths, or elſe return to priſon, he did judge that he ſhould have ſinned againſt God, and againſt thoſe over whom the Holy Ghoſt had made him overſeer, and againſt his family, and againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if he ſhould have returned to priſon for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing that which he had light to do. The caſe being thus (as it is known to hundreds to be) I ſhould hardly truſt my life, eſtate, or liberty in that mans hand, that ſhould trample upon the name of Mr. <hi>John Simpſon</hi> for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> The next uſe may be of Exhortation. Is it ſo, that it is a Chriſt-like frame of ſpirit to be deeply affected with, &amp; to mourn over the death of ſuch as are truly gracious; Then it concerns us ſeriouſly to conſider the providences of God this way, and that more generally, and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly. Firſt more generally, God hath lately made ſad breaches upon many of the families of his precious ſervants; many a flouriſhing ſami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath mouldred away in a little time: And God hath lately taken away many very famous inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108795:15"/>both Miniſters and others; ſo that we have cauſe to cry out with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Help Lord, for the godly man ceaſeth; for the faithful fail from among the children of men.</hi> Now this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of God calls for deep humiliation, and it becomes us to bow before God, and to meet him in the way of his judgments, leaſt his wrath break out further againſt us, and there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</p>
            <p>But 2d. and more particularly, I would beg you of this Congregation to conſider the preſent ſtroke of God upon you in taking away Mr. <hi>John Sympſon:</hi> And for the enforcing of this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I ſhall propoſe theſe few particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, This to me is a very ſpeaking providence. I know all the providences of God ſpeaks ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to us, but this ſpeaks very much; as, firſt it ſpeaks forth an immediate hand of God: God hath taken him from you, and not man. Now for God to take away his Miniſters at ſuch a day as this is, muſt needs be a ſpeaking providence; even at ſuch a day wherein men ſlay them civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſlay them in their teſtimony, and render them as naturally dead, for God then to take them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by death, is as much as if God ſhould ſay, Well, if my ſervants trouble you, if their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be a torment unto you, I'le take them from you, and provide for them in another world. You ſay they ſhal be as if they were naturally dead; and becauſe you ſay ſo, they ſhall be dead indeed: for God and man to be both at this work; man to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108795:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſlay them civilly, and God to ſlay them judicially, is ſurely matter of great lamentation.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. This ſtroke may ſpeak forth to many of you, a non improvement of ſo great a mercy as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of his Miniſtery was: I judg many of you preſent lived years under the Miniſtry of this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant of Chriſt, and his Miniſtry hath been unto you <hi>As a very lovely ſong,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.32</note> of one that hath a pleaſant voice, and can play well on an inſtrument: you have heard his words, but you would not do them.</hi> There hath not been a ſuitable converſation to ſuch a Miniſtry: A Goſpel, ſpiritual, heavenly Miniſtry, calls for a Goſpel, ſpiritual and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Converſation; ſuch was his Miniſtry, but ſuch (I fear) hath not been the converſation of many of his hearers. And indeed all of us that did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy more or leſs of his labours, have cauſe to mourn before the Lord this day for our non-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, that we were ſo vain and careleſs in our hearing; that we took no more care about the hearing, receiving, and practiſing what God was pleaſed to reveal unto us by his ſervant. This faithfull man might (according to the judgement of reaſon) have lived many years, &amp; done much ſervice: Now for God to take away his faithfull labourers in the midſt of their days, to cauſe their ſon to ſet at noon, is a providence that hath a dreadfull aſpect upon unfaithfull, and unfruitfull hearers. And indeed ſuch like ſtrokes tells us all, that Eternity draws on apace, that 'twil not be long ere the Kingdom of Chriſts patience be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108795:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>'twil be but as a day, and Chriſt ſhall ceaſe to make proffers of grace, and the ſpirit ſhal ceaſe to ſtrive with man, and all faithful Miniſters and Laborers ſhall ceaſe to pray and preach for ever: and thoſe unalterable words ſhall be made good, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11. <hi>Let him that is unjuſt be unjuſt ſtill,</hi> &amp;c. Oh! what would many a condemned wretch give at the great day to have Chriſt, and mercy, and pardon proffered to it then, as they have been many a time proffered in the Miniſtry of this glorified Saint? But know (O ſoul) that if thou dieſt deſpiſing and rejecting Chriſt and ſpiritual bleſſings, Chriſt will deſpiſe thee at that day; and then 'twil not be all thy crying and roaring that will ſave thee from the wrath of the Lamb, from everlaſting plagues and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. This diſpenſation of God may poſſibly ſpeak to many of you, a diſpiſing &amp; ſleighting the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and gifts of this holy man. In this generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of profeſſors hath been found a haughty proud ſpirit, a heart lifted up againſt God, and his honeſt ſincere hearted ſervants: No ſooner have perſons gotten a few airy notions of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but preſently they have been apt to ſlight, and trample upon, not onely thoſe that have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, but upon thoſe alſo who have infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (to ſpeak by way of compariſon) excelled them, both in parts, and grace. Now for God to take away his eminently gifted ſervants, doth very much condemn this proud and haughty ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108795:17"/>In ſuch kind of providences, God ſeemeth thus to ſpeak, Is it not enough, [O ye profeſſors of England] is it not enough, that my faithfull miniſters, &amp; labourers ſhould be reproached, and ſcorned, and trampled on by the prophane wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people, but you [my profeſſing people] muſt deſpiſe, and ſcorn them, and delight to grieve their ſpirits. When it may be a faithful ſervant of mine hath with prayers, and tears [ſecretly] ſought unto me for light in ſuch a ſcripture, or truth, and I have anſwered his prayer, and given him light therein, and he hath preacht unto you in my ſpirit, and fear, then (with a great deal of diſ-reſpect to my ſervant) you have brought forth your objections and cavils againſt the truth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and this not to ſatiſfie your ſelves in the knowledge of truth: It hath not been that you might know, love, and obey truth, but to pleaſe your itching ears, and your critical fancies; and ſo have ſent home my ſervant with a troubled and a perplexed ſpirit for your ſakes. Well, ſaith God, ſince it is ſo, that my ſervants teſtimony is a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the prophane, and their gifts, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deſpiſed by you, that profeſs my name, I'l take them out of the world, out of all your way, take them into mine own boſome, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where neither a ſcornful malicious ſinner, nor a proud profeſſor ſhall trouble, or grieve them more.</p>
            <p>This kind of ſpirit was in the Church of <hi>Corinth: Paul</hi> (that glorious preacher) was ſleighted by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108795:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>many of the gifted perſons of that Church,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10.</note> and it's not to be queſtioned, but that there were ſome in that Church that thought themſelves as wiſe as <hi>Paul,</hi> and as fit to preach as <hi>Paul,</hi> and to adviſe, and give counſell as <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But I would have perſons of this ſpirit, to weigh that text, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.30. ſaith God to Ezekiel, <hi>Alſo thou ſon of man, the children of thy people are ſtill a talking againſt thee by the walls, and in the doors of the houſes, and ſpeak one to another, every one to his brother, ſaying, Come, I pray you, and hear what is the word that cometh from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here God taketh notice of their ſecret whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt his Prophets, how they ſpoke againſt Ezekiel behind the door, and the wall, and ſaid (ſcoffingly) come, let us go hear what this <hi>Ezekiel</hi> will tell us from the Lord, what ſtorie of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and wrath he hath to prate of to day. My dearly beloved, God taketh notice of all thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſpeeches that are ſpoken ſecretly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his miniſters, he takes notice of that vain ſleight ſpirit that hath been among profeſſors; who have ſaid one to another, Come, lets go hear ſuch a man to day, hear what he will ſay, what news he will tel us, what he will ſpeak in the name of the Lord to us this day, &amp;c. Beloved, is there ever a ſoul in this congregation, that hath ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken againſt this faithfull ſervant of Chriſt, now in heaven? Oh! that God would break thy heart, and ſo ſanctify this preſent ſtroke, as that it may tend to humble thee under the ſenſe of thy ſin. And thus much for the firſt argument
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108795:18"/>to move to humiliation, <hi>viz.</hi> that the death of this faithfull ſervant of Chriſt, is a very ſpeaking providence.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, To move you to a ſenſe of this ſtroke conſider theſe two great circumſtances where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it was cloathed: Firſt, That God took him away immediately upon his releaſment out of Priſon, when you had ſome hopes of a further enjoyment of his labors: and Secondly, That God ſhould take him away at ſuch a time, a time wherein there is the greateſt want of faithful and zealous laborers, as hath been for many ſcores of years in <hi>England;</hi> eſpecially of ſuch as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned in, and zealous for Church-work; ſuch as have abilities for, and a heart to that great work of maintaining the people of God in their ſeparation from the world, and Antichriſtian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, A third motive to humiliation, is that near relation that was between this ſervant of the Lord, and many of you preſent: he was to many of you a faithful Paſtor and Teacher; who labored amongſt you in the Word and Doctrine. And mind what the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Smite the ſhepherd, and the ſheep ſhall be ſcattered, &amp;c.</hi> If the Lord prevent not, now the ſhepherd is ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten you'l be ſcattered; for it will be hard to find a perſon ſo ready to venture life and liberty to feed you, as undoubtedly (had God ſpared him) he would have been. And beſides, to many of you he might be a ſpiritual Father, a Father in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108795:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt, a means of your Conviction and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and oh! what hard hearts have you, if you cannot mourn over a dead Father, a dead ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, a faithful Paſtor when taken from you, &amp;c? But</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, conſider thoſe bleſſed qualifications wherewith this ſervant of Chriſt was beſpangled, and whereby he was inabled to ſerve the glory of God and your ſouls: As,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, he was one that had love for all Saints: he had room in his heart for every ſoul that he did judge to be received into the heart of Chriſt: he held communion with the Saints, not upon the account of this or that form, or name, but upon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the account of union with the Lord Jeſus: he loved no man upon the account of opinion, but upon the account of union with Chriſt, and this he hath declared many a time in this Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. There was hardly a member that he did in the name of Chriſt and the Church give the right hand of fellowſhip unto, but he did acquaint them with this his principle; told them that union with Chriſt was the ground of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among the Saints; and the reaſon of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was not their being of this or that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but for that they were judged perſons inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted in Chriſt, and ſuch who (by virtue of Chriſts purchaſe) were heirs of that glory above that muſt receive all Saints (not as Presbyters, or Independents, or Anabaptiſts, &amp;c.) but as Saints, into its everlaſting habitations.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:108795:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, He had great light in the doctrine of Free Grace, he had caſt anchorwithin the vail, and underſtood much of that great myſtery of the mercy ſeat. And indeed here lay the glory of his miniſtry, in holding forth the riches of Gods grace by Jeſus Chriſt. In the preaching of this Doctrine, he was a myſtery to this blind world, they could not underſtand him, and therefore hardly knew by what name to call him; and not onely ſo, but he was an offence to many profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; for they (not being able to reach him) did judge that he intended liberty to ſin, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he did often mention thoſe cautions laid down by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.2.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.17. And as at many other times, ſo (bleſſed be God) a little before his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, preaching from that text <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.15.16. &amp;c. he did ſo charge profeſſors with their luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs, and hypocriſie, and neglect of cloſet duty, and family duty, and Church duty, that he left a ſuſſicient teſtimony behind him, for the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of ſuch mouths for ever. But in this the ſervant was not above his Lord; for the Phariſees did thus charge Chriſt, they did charge him with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a friend to publicans and ſinners
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.19.</note>: Something of truth there was in this charge; for Chriſt he was the ſinners friend, but undoubtedly the intent of that charge was to accuſe Chriſt with being a friend to ſin, and with indulging ſin and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe in his followers; which was abominable; for though Chriſt loveth the ſinner, yet he hates
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108795:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſin with a perfect hatred.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.9.</note> Now if the wicked heart of man could thus charge Chriſt, it's no wonder that this his faithful ſervant ſhould thus be judged.</p>
            <p>And further, as he had great light in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, ſo he preacht that Doctrine with the greateſt alacrity, and raiſedneſs of ſpirit ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable. In the handling of other ſubjects he was more ſtreightned and diſcompoſed; but when he came to ſpeak of the unſearchable riches of the Grace of Chriſt, he was as an Angel of God, lifted up above himſelf: he had a flood of words, and yet ſeemed to want words to expreſs what he did know, and what he did enjoy of divine grace and favour. This being true (as thoſe that did live under his Miniſtry knows it to be) the loſs muſt needs be great.</p>
            <p>To loſe a pure Goſpel Preacher is a great loſs: Eternity depends upon a right underſtanding of the great Doctrine of Juſtification by Chriſt: Eternity depends not upon being baptized once or twice, upon this or the other Form; we may be guilty of miſtakes about the circumſtances of worſhip, and yet be happy; but if we miſtake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the greatmatter of our Juſtification by Chriſt, we are loſt for ever. And beſides, this Doctrine gives in the beſt comfort in the worſt times; gives peace in trouble, and joy in ſorrow, and life in death, &amp;c. When there are troubles without, and fears within, it is the conſideration of the Covenant of Grace alone that can eſtabliſh and ſettle the heart of a true believer.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:108795:20"/>
            <p>It's not ſo much the ſouls looking to the light within, or to its own qualifications, as to that perfect ſatisfaction that Chriſt made to divine juſtice for all its ſins in his own perſon, that muſt beget in the ſoul a well-grounded hope of eternal glory. All our inherent qualifications without an intereſt in the righteouſneſs and ſatisfaction of Chriſt, will leave us ſhort of heaven at the laſt. But</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, he was a faithful ſervant of Chriſt; faithful I ſay, and that both in reſpect to God, and alſo to the ſouls of ſuch to whom he preacht. Firſt faithful to God; in that whenever it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord to reveal ought of his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure unto him, whenever anything was warm up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſpirit, that he did judge to be from the Lord, out it came, let it pleaſe or diſpleaſe, hee would not bawk his light and conſcience upon no account whatever. He did not ſhun to declare unto you the whole counſel of God, ſo far as it was revealed untohim. And then his faithfulneſs unto your ſouls did appear in this, that if at any time he was convinced that he had delivered any thing that was not conſonant to Scripture, hee would publickly and openly confeſs his miſtake and error, and trample upon his own name and honor to ſecure your ſouls, that you might not be miſtaken and deceived through his means. That he did at any time miſtake, ſhews that he was a man ſubject to error, as the beſt of men are; that he did thus ingenuouſly and openly confeſs his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108795:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>error when convinced, ſhews that he was an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent faithful Chriſtian, faithful both to truth and the ſouls of his hearers. I am apt to think that many Preachers have taught erroneous and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doctrines, and thereby have ſeduced many; and that ſome of theſe Preachers have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that they have ſo done, but notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this conviction, the perſons ſeduced by them might go to hell in their miſtakes, before they would indeavor to reduce them, by making an open and publick acknowledgment of thoſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors which they have preacht. Man is a proud creature, and ſtands much upon his name and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; ſo that it is rare to find a perſon that is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (as Mr. <hi>Sympſon</hi> often hath done) to trample upon his name, though thereby he might lift up Chriſt's name, and ſave ſouls from dropping in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, he was a zealous ſervant of Chriſt, hee was willing to ſpend and bee ſpent that hee might fulfil his Miniſtry, and do your ſouls good. How laborious was he in preaching? how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant was he in attending upon the Aſſemblys of the Church? and how often hath he blamed you for neglecting thoſe Aſſemblys? He was not one that did the work of the Lord negligently, but with a fervent ſpirit he ſerved his God. He was not one that would indent with God before-hand, that would ſtand upon terms, ſaying, Lord, I'le ſerve thee, ſo my name, and eſtate, and liberty may be ſecured; but whatever he did judge to be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108795:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>his duty, he would preſently up and be doing, and leave the ſucceſs and bleſſing to the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/> Fifthly; he was an experimental Chriſtian, one that had much communion with God, and much experience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his goodneſs, as you have heard him often expreſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny a Preacher diſhes out largely to others, of that which he taſts but little himſelf. I am not to think, many a faithful Minister of Chriſt lives but low, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon to what this bleſſed Saint injoyed. By this his experience, he was enabled to ſpeak a word in due ſeaſon to the weary ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, he was a very humble condeſcending Chriſtian: How did he labour after thoſe things that might make for peace? he laboured always to maintain the unity of the ſpirit, in the bond of peace: he would condeſcend to the meaneſt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church for peace ſake. If he fail'd in any thing, it was in that he was too apt to be drawn away by the perſwaſions of his brethren, and could not carry on Church matters with that authority, majeſtie, ſeverity, and ſpirit of government, which he might (according to ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture rule) have done, to the reproof, and ſhame of ſuch, who are deſirous of, and content with the enjoyment of Church previledge; but are too high and proud to ſubmit unto Church diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are deverſities of operations, but it is the ſame God which worketh all in all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.6.</note> For to one is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a ruling ſpirit, to another, a healing ſpirit:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108795:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>But all theſe worketh that one and the ſelf ſame ſpirit, dividing to every man ſeverally as he will.</hi> And the works and graces of God in his people, are to be honoured and admired according as they ſhine forth in their operations and diverſities. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and rule is that moſt men ſeek after. It's hard to find a perſon that is gifted, willing to condeſcend (even in thoſe things wherein he may) to thoſe Chriſtians that are below him for peace ſake. A healing ſpirit is a glorious ſpirit, and a ſpirit much wanting among the people of God in England. To loſe therefore a Chriſtian of a healing compoſing ſpirit, is a great loſs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, He was a holy man. After the Lord was pleaſed to work upon him by his mighty ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and power, and to reveal the riches of grace thorow Chriſt unto his ſoul, he was (as is known to many) of a heavenly converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>He walked cloſe with God in his family; he was not a ſaint abroad, and a Divel at home; but made it appear that he was really good, by this, that he was relatively good; good in his relations; a good husband, a good father, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſate looſe from this world; he made not gain his godlineſs; he did not deſign to make mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chandize of Chriſt and the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>He hath often denied mony for preaching, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially funerall Sermons; and if any were forced upon him, or ſent after him, he would ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of it to the poor.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:108795:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>His diſcourſe was moſtly heavenly, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall: If other diſcourſe was in hand, he was but dull company, he had little to ſay: but if the conference were heavenly, he was as upon the wing, as a fiſh in the water, and a bird in the air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be here objected, that <hi>Mr. Sympſon</hi> was in his younger years of a vain and ſlight conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; I anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Divine love rideth in greateſt tryumph, when it hath the greateſt ſinners following it as it's captives.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Some in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> that did heartily cloſe with Chriſt, were before their converſion very vile, and wicked; ſee 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10.11. <hi>Such were ſome of you: but ye are waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. but</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This bleſſed ſaint would to his dying day acknowledge his former vanity, and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, to his own ſhame, and the lifting up of the riches of free grace through the blood of Chriſt: and mind what the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to forgive our ſins, and to cleanſ us from all unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the 4th. motive to humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was drawn from the qualifications of this ſervant of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The 5th. and laſt motive to humiliation is, to conſider the great bleſſing, and ſucceſs that did attend his miniſtry: He was (through Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108795:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>inſtrumental for the converſion of many ſouls, he hath l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft behind him many ſeals of his miniſtry. Every faithful laborious preacher is not attended with ſuch a bleſſing. Many a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miniſter hath <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> commiſion (<hi>Chap.</hi> 6.10.) <hi>To make the heart of his people fat, and their ears heavy;</hi> (dreadful work) <hi>and to ſhut their eies: leſt they ſee with their eies, and hear with their ears, and underſtand with their heart, and convert, and be healed.</hi> It was the ſaying of a godly Miniſter in <hi>England,</hi> after ſome years preaching to a people, <hi>That he had preach'd his people dead:</hi> I ſay not, but that many might be the more fit for hell by the means of Mr. <hi>Sympſon</hi>'s miniſtry; it might (through the wickedneſs of the hearers) be the ſavour of death unto death to many: but this I ſay, that God bleſt him above ſcores, nay hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Preachers in the great work of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in turning ſouls from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God, &amp;c. Now to loſe a Miniſter, whoſe miniſtry was attended with ſo great a bleſſing (eſpecially at ſuch a time, when it is rare to hear of one new Convert) muſt needs be a great loſs. I ſhal here in the cloſe of this Exhortation ſpeak a word or two by way of Caution;<note place="margin">Caution.</note> and that</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Though this ſtroke of God be a matter of ſorrow and humiliation, yet you muſt take heed of a murmuring ſpirit: You have cauſe to bee diſpleaſed with your ſelves, and your ſins, but not with God; and that</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:108795:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Becauſe God takes away nothing but what he firſt gave. The perſon and gifts of this Saint, were given unto you by the Lord; he hath taken nothing but his own. Learn therefore to ſay with <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 1.21— <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You have no cauſe to murmure, and that becauſe you had ſorfeited this mercy long ago: that God continued the Miniſtry of this his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſo long among you, was a fruit of his ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounding love.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Though you are to mourn under this ſtroke, yet take heed of mourning as thoſe without hope; without hope I ſay, 1. With reſpect to him; his happineſs is unqueſtionable: your loſs is his gain. He is taken up into glory, and hath there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God. He is out of the reach of all his enemies, they can now impriſon him no more. He is where hee'l never have any thing impoſed upon him contrary to Conſcience: hee'l never ſuffer there for Non-conformity ſake. There God is ſerved, adored and glorified with one heart, and with one conſent. 2. Mourn not without hope with reſpect to your ſelves, as if God were not able to make up this loſs. I remember a relation of a Lady, from whom it pleaſed God to take an onely Son, that ſometime after a friend coming to viſit her, and bemoaning this her ſad loſs, ſhe breaks forth into theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, [I profeſs (ſaith ſhe) God can never make me amends for the taking away of that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108795:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Son] A dreadful ſpeech it was; take heed (my friends) of this ſpirit. It's true, your loſs is great, but God is able to ſupply it; and that either</p>
            <p n="1">1. By cauſing the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> to fall upon <hi>Eliſha,</hi> by anointing and raiſing up of ſome other to head and feed you in the room of this his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. Or 2ly, he can feed you himſelf without a Miniſter: God can fill up the room of Miniſtry and Ordinances. Indeed let God be abſent, and there's nothing can fill up his room: It's not huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, wife, children, eſtate, liberty, Paſtors, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, &amp;c. can ſupply the want of God: but now let God be preſent, and that is above, and more then all. And undoubtedly, if God deny you a publick Goſpel-Miniſtry, it's your duty to wait upon him for more ſecret and immediate feedings. I am afraid, that as formerly profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors were greatly guilty of ſleighting and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the means and miniſtry of the Goſpel, ſo now they will be guilty of Idolizing the Ordinance of publick Preaching at ſuch a rate, as to think themſelvs bound and obliged to hear men of any principles or practices, rather then to neglect that Ordinance—Arminians, Socinians, Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, &amp;c. any thing, every thing, rather then be out of publick worſhip. Take heed of mourning in a ſpirit of unbelief, ſaying, Can God ſpread a table in the wilderneſs? can God feed and teach without a Preacher. To live without the true worſhip of God is bad, but to be found in a way of falſe worſhip is worſe. It's my duty to omit
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:108795:24"/>that Ordinance of Chriſt, which I can't enjoy without ſin.</p>
            <p>Thus much for that part of the Exhortation, which relates to Humiliation: I ſhall give you two brief words further, and ſo cloſe. Firſt, Is it ſo that the death of faithful inſtruments is a matter of great Humiliation;</p>
            <p>Then let this ſtirr you up to be earneſt with the Lord, that he would continue and preſerve thoſe faithful miniſters that do yet remain, that he would double his ſpirit upon them: hide them in the ſecret of his preſence: increaſe their number; Not forgetting the prayer of <hi>Moſes</hi> for the tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> (<hi>Deut.</hi> 33.11.) in theſe words. <hi>Bleſs, Lord, his ſubſtance, and except the work of his hands; ſmite through the loins of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not again.</hi> Theſe words ſhall undoubtedly be made good with reſpect unto the miniſtry of the Goſpel, Chriſt will in his time ſmite through the loins of them that riſe up againſt a Goſpel miniſtry; hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and deſpitefully uſing his faithfull ſervants, &amp; hee'l ſo pierce through their loyns, as that they ſhall fall, and never riſe more.</p>
            <p>In the mean time take heed you that profeſs the name of Chriſt, that you do not endanger the reſt of the faithful labourers that are left amongſt you; and that neither, 1. By ſlighting and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the meaneſt of them, 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 36.16. <hi>But they mocked the meſſengers of God, and deſpiſed his words, miſuſed his prophets, untill the wrath of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108795:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt his people, till there was no remedy.</hi> Nor Secondly, By idolizing thoſe that are moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. How many famous inſtruments (to ſpeak according to man's judgement) hath the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of this age ſent to their graves before their time, by idolizing their perſons and gifts, aſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that honor and glory to them, which was due to Chriſt alone? This ſpirit and frame hath even forced the Lord (in order to the convincing and humbling of his people) either to take away the ſpirit of zeal and courage from ſuch inſtruments, &amp; thereby render them unfit for further ſervice, or elſe to remove them by death from earth to heaven, out of the ſight of all his people that dwell in tabernacles of corrupt clay.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Such ſtrokes ſhould teach us all to provide for death. God takes away our leaders, and we muſt follow them: thoſe that would not follow the counſel and adviſe of Mr. <hi>Sympſon</hi> while living, muſt follow him to the grave now dead; to the grave wee muſt all go, and the Lord knows how ſoon; Of what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port therefore is it, that we all manage mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſo while we live, as that when we com to die we may dye in peace, &amp; in ful aſſurance of our entrance into glory? We ſhould manage all our matters ſo in this world, as thoſe that muſt once dye, and come to judgement: performing every thing with this proviſo, <hi>That I may dye well.</hi> I am ſo to buy, ſell, and converſe with creatures, <hi>that I may dye well.</hi> I am ſo to hear, pray, read, receive the ſupper, have communion with the ſaints, as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108795:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>that I may dye well,</hi> dye in peace; all is to be done in order to dying well. My beloved, this life is the trimming chamber unto eternity: by all the means and mercies that thou doſt injoy, thou art fitting either to bear the eternal weight of glory, or the eternal weight of wrath: thou art fitting either for heaven, or hell: thou wilt either be bound up in the bundle of life, or elſe thou wilt be bound up for hell fire: Now the Lord give us all hearts to provide for that everlaſting ſtate. Amen, and Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 1. <hi>line laſt, for</hi> ſecret <hi>read</hi> ſevere; <hi>and what literal miſtakes or miſ-pointings-hath eſcaped the Preſs, you are deſired to amend as you find them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108795:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
